CONDOLENCES, DATO' MEOR ABDUL
RAHMAN BIN DAENG UDA MOHD HASHIM
SUPREME GRANDMASTER OF SILAT
GAYONG MALAYSIA
THIS FILM IS INSPIRED BY THE TRUE STORY
AND STRUGGLES OF THE LATE
DATO' MEOR ABDUL RAHMAN.
SOME OF THE EVENTS DEPICTED IN THIS FILM
ARE FICTIONAL AND DO NOT REPRESENT
ANY INDIVIDUALS OR ACTUAL EVENTS.
ANY RESEMBLANCE IS COINCIDENTAL.
INSPIRED BY A TRUE STORY
IN 1945, JAPAN SURRENDERED.
IN 1952, MEOR RETURNED TO SINGAPORE
AFTER BRITISH REOCCUPATION.
UNFORTUNATELY, SECRET SOCIETIES, GAMBLING,
PROSTITUTION, AND OPIUM ADDICTION
WERE WIDESPREAD.
THE POLICE SQUAD
WENT THROUGH A DARK PERIOD
DUE TO CORRUPTION
Brother Mat.
Hey! Where’s my money?!
Hurry up!
Hey! How dare you not to pay！
Don’t you dare run away!
Where are you trying to go?
Hey!
My child is sick. I need money.
Today, you’re sick.
Tomorrow, he’s sick.
And the day after tomorrow, he is sick.
Everyone else has paid.
Do you think you’re special?
Ah Keong, Sui Gu.
Enough!
Who are you?
Brother Mat.
Oh, newcomer.
Have you paid yet?
Protection money!
Don’t play a fool with me!
Hurry up and pay!
Don’t bother her.
If you bother her, I will call the police.
Weakling!
Snacks!
Cucur badak, ondeh-ondeh!
-How much for one cucur badak?
-Five cents.
Thank you.
Snacks!
Cucur badak, ondeh-ondeh!
How did you know I was here?
That sound of your breathing, Mat.
It sounds like a buffalo’s breathing.
I can hear it from five miles away.
And even more so right behind the door.
A face like this,
and you still want to try again.
You’re too slow.
Do it again.
Too greedy.
Watch your words first. Do it again.
Great! Continue!
Since when has a hole been here?
Pay attention to your surroundings, Mat.
Turn that into a strength.
A good practitioner will always be
aware of their surroundings.
What's with that hole?
Sister Chom put it there.
She wants to make a vegetable garden.
Fatimah! Good morning.
Good morning, Uncle.
Have a safe journey.
Alright.
Snacks!
How come there’s no one inside?
That's right, Teacher.
The thugs I caught at the night market,
what happened to them?
What has happened to them, Teacher?
I don’t know either.
Hey, you!
Did you see anyone inside the lockup?
-No, sir.
-No?
Don’t mess with me.
Help me a bit.
Teacher,
I am definitely sure.
No one has been inside that lockup
since the start of the morning shift.
And…
and…
and I am definitely sure
no one has come here, Teacher.
Hurry up.
I am innocent, sir.
Peter Malcolm?
Why should I have written it
if you were just going to say it out loud?
Oh, and Meor…
He blacked out!
He is knocked out.
The undefeated winner is Peter Malcolm.
Come on!
Let me help you.
What's that, Brother?
Not sure.
When I pass my exam,
I want to drive a truck like that too.
Is Uncle Mat handsome?
But what if Uncle Mat fails again?
Hey, kid,
did you have too much sugar or what?
SAKURA CLUB
Hey, Malcolm.
HU WEI TANG
Thank you, Boss Khoon.
Here.
Just bear it.
Grandma said if you apply it like this,
the bruise marks will fade quickly.
Mayang.
Yes?
If I pass the examination,
I can become a police officer.
-Really?
-Yes.
That means I will get a permanent job.
That’s good if that’s the case.
After this…
can you…
What is it?
Can you…
-What it is?
-Will you share my happiness?
Of course, Brother Mat.
My prayers are always
with you, Brother Mat.
Why is it so hard to say?
-Miss.
-Yes?
Have you already closed your stall?
Not yet.
Can I have one cendol?
Sure. Please wait a moment.
Here!
Which type of cendol do you want?
As usual. With extra peanuts.
Extra peanuts.
Is that even possible?
The doctor said I’m overweight.
This isn’t being overweight,
it’s happiness.
Happiness.
Listen to the doctor
and eat less oily food.
Who are you?
-Fauzi.
-Fauzi?
Good morning, everyone.
-Good morning, Teacher.
Fauzi, you are here.
Meor.
No need to be too formal.
Friends, this is Fauzi,
my partner starting today.
-Teacher.
-What?
Teacher, do you remember
this person, Worawut?
Worawut?
That Muay Thai fighter?
What’s wrong with this Thai guy?
Looking for trouble all around the world?
Who is he? Wuro what？
Worawut.
Listen to what I’m about to tell you.
Can you believe that arrogant Worawut
got beaten up by our Panglima Sendo Perak?
Panglima Sendo of Perak？
Hey!
There.
That was the best fight I’ve ever seen.
Rizal, come show us.
Wrong person.
Ali.
Fight!
This is how he fought back.
Ali, you be Worawut.
-Who?
-Worawut.
Oh, Worawut.
-Take it slow, Ali.
-Alright.
-Teacher blocked.
-What did Teacher do after that?
-Catch him.
-What happened next?
-Teacher caught him like this.
-Then?
-Then Teacher did this.
-Ouch!
Was it like this, Teacher?
It wasn't that dramatic,
not to that extent.
Thank you, Ali.
Teacher,
if I were you,
I’d beat him until even his parents
didn't recognize him.
Why bother hitting
an opponent who is already down?
That will only prevent him
from receiving the lesson
that God has prepared for him.
Teacher,
is it true that all silat grandmasters
are invulnerable?
Nonsense. Bullshit.
We shouldn’t believe things like that.
It’s already 1950.
We're in the modern age,
the era of science and industry.
If your child is sick,
would you take him to the hospital
or to a traditional healer?
We are all civil servants.
How can we believe
in mumbo jumbo stuff like that?
Hey, newbie,
it’s not good to speak like that.
I’m here to work,
not to socialize.
Don’t you have any manners?
Manners?
Manners won’t get our work done.
This.
This is what gets our work done.
All that fuss earlier
doesn't stand a chance against this.
Never point that at your own people.
There’s not even a bullet in there.
Of course there isn’t. If there had been,
my head would've been blown off.
Hey, kid.
You still have a lot to learn.
Listen to me.
Even a pistol isn’t the fastest weapon.
Learn from who? From you?
At least I still can see
my own feet when I bend down.
What Pak Man said is true.
A pistol isn’t always faster.
Bullshit.
You were just lucky earlier
because I wasn’t ready.
What about this?
If you can prove that he’s right,
I will apologize to him.
-Teacher, there’s no need.
-It’s okay, Pak Man.
Thank you for being willing
to train with me.
Teacher!
Such power, Teacher!
"Bullshit."
Keep it. I don’t smoke.
Don’t take too long.
We still have a lot of work
that needs to be done.
I want to find all the cases that
Peter Malcolm closed three years ago.
What?
Many of these files don't have labels.
In that case,
we’d better start right away.
Today, there’s been progress in the case.
If I keep going,
I will definitely find the truth.
I don’t know how far this thing goes
or how many people are involved.
Should I continue?
Are you worried
that others might be affected?
That's it?
I thought it was
something really serious just now.
This is serious, Chom.
Dear, do you remember
what you told me
before you took this police job?
You said
you wanted to do the right thing.
For God,
for yourself,
for your family,
and for the people.
So right now,
are you still doing the right thing?
There.
That’s the answer.
Do not doubt.
Do not be afraid.
God says,
"Do not fear,
for I am with you."
"I hear and see everything."
Mat.
Can I ask for your help?
I'm currently investigating a case,
and I'll be quite busy.
I might be spending
a lot of time at the station,
so I want to ask for your help
to look after Sister Chom
and the kids at home.
Of course.
You can count on me.
Just leave everything to me.
Thank you, Mat.
We know that Malcolm accepted bribes,
but it's not clear from whom.
We’ll investigate all his cases
from the past three years.
We’ll check and cross-reference
with those who were arrested.
IDENTIFIED
The Sungai Gang had
a total of 128 arrests.
The Tiger Clan had a total of 24 arrests.
Twenty-four?
In a period of three years,
out of a total of 384 arrests,
they only had 24?
If Malcolm's working with Lee Khoon,
he must protect these places from raids.
Next, we just need to identify
which places belong to the Tiger Clan
by following the people from Lee Khoon
who collect protection money.
PROSPERITY
Hey! You still haven't paid?
Watch out. I'll beat you up!
After we identify them,
we will raid those places.
Malcolm must have something.
We’ll use the opportunity
to gather evidence
that Malcolm and Lee Khoon
are working together.
He still hasn’t left with the bag.
This is weird.
So what should we do?
Do we need to include
this place in the list too?
What is this place?
I want to go take a look.
I will follow you.
No.
Why?
Not suitable.
I’ll go in for a moment. You wait here.
Sir.
What are you doing here?
What happened?
Hey, why are you taking off your clothes?
Oh, great.
Say it. Tell me, what's happening?
Hey!
Do you know who I am?
What are you going to do to me?
All of you better remember
you’ll be in big trouble
if anything happens to me.
-Understand?
-Who are you?
You are a dead man.
But don’t be afraid.
This is my boss’s place.
No one will know you died here!
Hey!
Whoever kills him first
will gets triple the money from me!
Kill him!
Fauzi,
get out of here now.
Yeah!
I want to say thank you
for saving me at that place.
You would’ve done the same for me.
No.
I don’t think I would’ve done
the same, because…
-I don’t have your…
-"Mumbo Jumbo?"
Skills.
And I should apologize
for what I said earlier about silat.
Fauzi.
I'm not affected
by what you said.
But some of our friends
were hurt by it.
Understood.
I will apologize to Pak Man and Rizal.
Actually, there’s one
more thing I want to say.
Is it okay if I call you "teacher" too?
And learn silat from you?
You’re a graduate
with a scholarship, right?
Yes.
There's fish, pineapple.
-Brother.
-Yes?
-Where is the cendol shop?
-Over there.
-Thank you.
-You're welcome.
-Mayang.
-Yes?
My name is Fauzi.
Brother Meor sent me.
Where's Mat?
You are Brother Mat's friend?
Brother Mat will be here in a moment.
Please have a seat first.
-Do you want cendol?
-It's okay.
-No need to trouble you.
-No worries.
-Brother Mat’s friend is my friend too.
-Ah.
No worries. Please have a seat first.
Brother Fauzi.
-I'm sorry.
-It's okay.
I didn’t mean to.
-Hey!
-Brother Mat!
Fake Malay!
Brother Mat!
Brother Fauzi!
-Please don’t fight!
-What's wrong with you?
What's wrong with you?
Didn't I already tell you
not to fight, Brother Mat?
Serves you right!
Here.
Twenty cents.
Why is it so expensive?
This vegetable was imported
from the Cameron Highlands.
You were saying that
Brother Meor asked you to come?
Yes.
I’m here to help you pass the examination.
So?
Why were you holding Mayang's hand?
When did I hold her hand?
The cendol fell. I was holding
the bowl, not her hand.
Fake Malay,
I'm sorry.
I really need to pass this exam.
Please help me.
Oh, my, what has
Teacher Meor gotten me into?
Continue.
-Ah, Chai!
-Yes, Teacher.
Keep your stances lower.
Alright, Teacher.
Continue.
So tired.
Time to learn!
Ugh,
let me rest for a day. Just a day.
We can continue tomorrow.
Tomorrow?
So you don’t want to pass, right?
Come on. What are you waiting for?
Do you want me to pass or not?
-You!
-Watch my head. You'll mess up my brain.
Since when do you have a brain?
Do you want to teach or not?
I'll be right back.
Thank you, Brother Mat,
for taking me home.
You are welcome.
I won’t let you go home alone.
Brother Mat, if you pass your exam later,
I want to buy you a gift.
No need.
Keep that money.
Leave it. It's my money.
Brother!
Brother! I managed
to answer all the questions!
My mind didn’t go blank this time.
Fauzi!
Thank you!
Listen.
Your hard work paid off. Praise be to God.
Hopefully, before long,
we can become colleagues!
I want to tell Mayang! I’m going now!
Don’t forget tomorrow!
Sister Chom has invited
everyone for dinner.
Alright!
There’s a ship with a suspicious weight
coming from Hong Kong.
It’s registered under the name Lee Geok.
Lee Geok?
That’s Lee Khoon’s adopted child.
Jade.
It’s scheduled to arrive tonight.
If Lee Khoon’s adopted child is here,
the item must be important.
Do you think those items
are what we think they are?
There’s only one way to be sure.
Alright. Listen up, everyone.
This is an emergency operation.
We will move straight
to the warehouse to carry out a raid.
If you encounter anyone, I repeat,
if you encounter anyone
who doesn’t cooperate,
just detain them.
-Police!
-Freeze!
Don't move!
This is a search warrant.
You are all required to cooperate.
Anyone who resists will be arrested!
Teacher.
Wait a moment, Teacher, I’ll keep looking.
There’s more, Teacher!
There’s really a lot of opium here.
Enough to fill an entire truck!
Boss Khoon!
What happened?
Boss Khoon, our warehouse!
It’s been raided by the police!
What about the goods?
They were all seized by the police!
-Where’s Geok?
-Arrested by the police.
Tell Malcolm to come to see me.
Attention!
HU WEI TANG
-Put this in living room, please.
-Alright, Sister Chom.
Aishah.
Aishah, it’s Cik Mat's turn.
-Mat.
-Yes?
Come here.
-You all go ahead and play first.
-Okay.
-Sister Mayang, come play with us.
That's far.
-You ready?
-Yes.
Mat!
Sister Chom!
Mayang!
Save the children!
Mat!
-Sister Chom!
-Mom!
Kak Chom!
Mat!
Mom!
Let us go! Let go! Mom!
Mat!
Mom!
I want to ask you to please look after
Sister Chom and the kids at home.
Of course.
You can count on me.
Just leave everything to me.
Thank you, Mat.
Mat!
Sister Mayang!
Fauzi.
There’s a celebration for Mat tonight.
-Let’s go back early.
-Sure.
We’re heading out first, guys.
Goodbye, Teacher.
Let go of my children!
Let go!
Mom!
Let us go!
Mat!
Cik Mat!
Sister Mayang.
Kak Mayang.
Come quickly!
How pitiful.
What happened?
Hurry!
I’m sorry…
I’ve disappointed you.
You did your best.
I’m proud of you.
I understand.
Repeat what I say.
Okay?
I bear witness
that there is no god but Allah.
Repeat after me.
I bear witness
that there is no god but Allah.
And I bear witness
that Muhammad is the messenger of Allah.
Brother Mat!
God!
Ugh!
Go check the goods.
Ah Keong!
Boss, the goods are all here!
Freeze!
Now, let my family go.
Sure.
Don't move!
Dad!
-Mom!
-Aisyah.
Dad!
Mat!
Where's Mat?
Malcolm!
Fauzi!
Take my family out from here.
There is a debt that needs to be paid.
Dad!
Gayong! In line!
Gayong, ready!
Listen! Basic punch!
One!
Two!
Three!
Four!
Basic punching and blocking! One!
Two!
Three!
Four!
Stand at ease!
Gayong! Salute to the front!
One! Two! Three! One!